PROFESSOR: Let's take a look.
Here's this tree-structured CSP.
We've already ordered it.
After we have an ordering, we have an
algorithm where we enforce consistency
of arcs from right to left, and then
we assign from left to right.
My first claim is that after the
backward pass, where we visit the arcs
one by one, enforcing their consistency
one time, that all of the
arcs in this direction are consistent.
I'm not saying anything about
the other direction, right.
So let's see if we can figure
out why that claim is true.
Well, let's think.
Let's think about an individual arc.
For example, let's think about this
arc here from B to D. Right.
Here's an arc.
At some point in this algorithm, I
looked at it, and I made it consistent
by deleting things from B. So there
was a point at which it was
consistent.
And the question is, could my further
processing mess that up.
Well what I do after this.
I changed, possibly, something about
the arc from B to C and from A
to B, and so on.
But basically, all of the arcs I touch
after this one are on the left.
Which means all of the domains that I
could possibly delete values from are
on the left.
And when do I have to revisit this
arc to make it consistent again.
What domain is important.
The head, so as long as D here doesn't
lose a value from its domain, this
arc, once consistent,
will stay that way.
And because nothing in this algorithm
will then delete a value
from D, we're good.
So once I've done this single pass, all
of these arcs in this direction a
consistent.
Not the other direction, but I don't
care about the other direction for
this algorithm.
All right.
So now we know that after this pass, all
of the arcs in this direction are
consistent.
The second claim is, if all of the
route-to-leaf arcs, these directions,
are consistent, then forward assignment
will not backtrack.
And we've already basically
seen why that's true.
Right.
And we can do an induction
on position.
So at the beginning you're fine.
You assign something to A, and whatever
you assign to A, because A to
B is consistent, you can extend to
B. What's the important bit.
The important bit here is that, for
example, when I get to, let's say, E--
and if I'm thinking about making an
assignment at E --if D-to-E is
consistent, and I've assigned something
to D, I'm guaranteed there's
a value at E which will continue
to satisfy the constraints.
So that's great but why don't I have an
algorithm that works for any CSP.
Where in this do we actually use
the fact that this is a tree.
Well, an important place we used it,
is what if E had another parent.
What if there were an arc from C-to-E.
And so the arc from D-to-E, let's say
it were consistent, and the arc from
C-to-E is also consistent.
And I say great.
I have a value at D, which means I can
extend it to an assignment at E. I
have a value at C, and that means I can
extend it to an assignment at E.
Why isn't that enough.
Problem is, the value that is safe that
E, based on what I did at D, and
the value that's safe at E based
on what I did at C may
not be the same value.
Arc consistency doesn't let you have two
things happening at once, be safe
at the same time.
That would be some higher
order of consistency.
So for tree-structured CSPs,
arc consistency--
in fact we're not even enforcing full
arc consistency --is enough to
guarantee that you won't backtrack.
But once you have cycles,
all bets are off.
The basic idea where a tree structure
ensures that the steps that you take
kind of don't reenter and interact again
in a bad way, we have that here
in CSP's, and we'll see it again
later for Baye's nets.